All right, let's talk about Lyndon B.
Johnson's Great Society, y'all. And get
excited because if modern American
liberalism was a bodybuilder, then the
Great Society was the moment those pecs
were popping the hardest of all American
history. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, now hopefully you'll remember from
a couple of videos ago when I showed you
that in the post-war years, the economy
was going positively bonkers, and that
led to a generalized economic prosperity
for the American population. But, turn
your ear holes this way and don't miss
that I just said generalized prosperity,
which is to say not every American had
pockets overflowing with post-war boom
boom. No, much of that wealth was
concentrated in the growing middle class
who had fled from the cities and settled
in suburban developments. And while mass
culture presented on television might
paint the picture that everyone was
doing well, about 1/5 of the American
population was impoverished and
struggled to survive in a land of plenty
all around them. And this drastic
inconsistency was highlighted by the
immensely popular book called The Other
America, written by socialist Michael
Harrington. Unfortunately, not related
to everyone's favorite Harrington.
Anyway, in his book, Harrington took
more than a little umbrage with the
claims of American politicians who like
to say that America's economic
prosperity had led largely to the
elimination of poverty in the United
States. And Harrington argued that the
reason such a claim was so easy for the
mass of Americans to believe is that the
impoverished didn't actually live in the
places where affluent Americans live.
Like most of these invisible poor lived
either in city ghettos or in the rural
countryside, and since most affluent
Americans lived in the suburbs away from
such places, they had no idea that
poverty was a much bigger problem than
they ever imagined. And so, this book
and the ideas associated with it
inspired liberal presidents in the 1960s
to take the decisive action that
attempted to directly address the
problem of poverty. For example, John F.
Kennedy cast his vision for a new
frontier, which was a set of policy
proposals that, among other things, took
aim at eliminating poverty and disease.
And in Kennedy's mind, the New Frontier
was simply an extension of Franklin
Roosevelt's New Deal policies, but the
difference was that the New Frontier
wasn't responding to an acute economic
crisis like the Great Depression.
Instead, New Frontier policies and the
Great Society policies that came later
were responding to systemic
socioeconomic inequality. Anyway, like
Roosevelt, Kennedy was a liberal who
believed in the power of the government
to address the social problems of the
population. However, unlike Roosevelt,
Kennedy was only able to make modest
gains on his New Frontier proposals
because he faced a stiff resistance from
a coalition of congressional
conservatives who wanted nothing more
than to smack that liberal smirk right
off his face. But then, in November of
1963, Kennedy was assassinated, and his
vice president, Lyndon B. Johnson, would
pick up the dangling threads of the New
Frontier and push it even further than
JFK even dreamed, thus leading the
United States into the golden age of
modern liberalism. And look, whether the
thought of such pervasive liberalism
draws a great cheer from your chest or
makes you want to open your mouth a
little, there's at least one thing
everyone watching this can agree on. You
want to get a five on that national
APUSH exam that's only a month away. And
if so, you should check out my APUSH
Heimler review guide, which has all the
materials you need to study as fast as
possible, and that link is in the
description. Anyway, for the next year,
Johnson made bold moves to carry out the
liberal legislative agenda left by his
predecessor. But, in the election of
1964, he ran for president on his own
terms in hopes of receiving his own
mandate from the American voters. And as
it turned out, Johnson got every bit of
that mandate. He won that election by an
even wider margin than Roosevelt did in
his second election, and Johnson
interpreted that to mean that he had the
people's confidence to enact
wide-ranging liberal policies in the
coming term. And so, Johnson summarized
his vision for America under the moniker
The Great Society, which aimed to
eliminate poverty and racial
discrimination in the United States.
Now, to put it simply, the Great Society
was essentially the New Deal 2.0. It
shared the same liberal assumptions that
government intervention is the most
effective way to cure the ills facing
American society, but it wasn't every
way bigger and more muscular than the
New Deal. And while the Great Society
included a dizzying amount of domestic
policy proposals, I'm just going to
mention two big categories that you're
going to need to know. First of all, the
Great Society aimed to address the
problem of racial inequality. And if you
know anything about Lyndon B. Johnson,
then maybe you just grew a question mark
over your head. That's because during
his time as a senator from Texas,
Johnson had opposed civil rights
legislation with a great aplomb. But as
president, Johnson was all, "Come on,
y'all know I love black people." and
worked to pass sweeping legislation to
guarantee their civil rights. So, what
changed? Well, probably the most
significant factor was that the Civil
Rights Movement was in full swing by
this point, and that put enormous
pressure on Johnson to respond and to
show that he was a president for all
Americans, not just some Americans. And
respond he did, not least because while
the nation was mourning the
assassination of Kennedy, Johnson saw an
opportunity to push Kennedy's civil
rights legislation through as a fitting
tribute. For example, Johnson led
Congress in passing two landmark pieces
of civil rights legislation. In 1964,
Congress passed the Civil Rights Act,
which mandated the end of legal
discrimination and racial segregation in
the United States. Furthermore, the law
prohibited discrimination based on race,
color, religion, sex, or national origin
in public facilities, in employment, in
federally funded education programs, and
in public accommodations like hotels and
restaurants and theaters, etc. And then
the next year, Johnson led Congress to
pass the Voting Rights Act of 1965 in
response to the pressure coming from all
sides in the Civil Rights Movement. And
so, the passage of this law illegalized
all efforts to discriminate at the
voting booth and gave Congress the right
to oversee elections in Southern states
to ensure compliance. But, the second
and perhaps most robust provision of the
Great Society was what Johnson called
the War on Poverty. The first
legislative move on this front was the
passage of the Economic Opportunity Act
of 1964, which offered impoverished
Americans an astonishing array of
services, including food stamps and rent
assistance. Also under this heading was
the Job Corps, which provided free
education and vocational training to
young adults to help them start their
lives on solid economic footing. And
then you had the Head Start program,
which provided low-income children with
free preschool and nutritional support
so that they might be better prepared to
enter primary school. You see, Johnson
believed that poverty was cyclical, and
without intervention, it would simply be
passed on from parents to children. And
so, Johnson aimed to break that cycle
with programs like Head Start. And then,
to address the medical needs of
impoverished children and the elderly,
Congress passed legislation that
provided government-funded health
insurance for both of those populations.
So, Medicare paid healthcare costs for
Americans over the age of 65, while
Medicaid did so for impoverished
children. And despite heavy opposition
from a conservative coalition in
Congress, the passage of these
provisions serve as an illustration of
how willing Americans were to embrace
the doctrines of modern liberalism. And
then, third and finally, Johnson's
expansion of liberalism also washed away
much of the anti-immigrant restrictions
that had been put in place in the 1920s.
For example, in 1965, Congress passed
the Immigration and Nationality Act,
which abolished the quotas enacted
against immigrants from Southern and
Eastern European nations, as well as
non-Western nations. And as a result,
immigration from Asia, Latin America,
and the Middle East increased
significantly and permanently changed
the demographic makeup of American
society. And so, that's what modern
liberalism looked like when it was at
the height of its bodybuilding career.
But, soon enough, a powerful coalition
of conservatives would get tired of the
leftist pec bouncing and mount a
comeback of their own. But, we'll have
to save that for its own video. Okay,
you can click here to watch all my other
Unit 8 videos, or you can click here to
grab my APUSH Heimler review guide,
which has everything you need to study
as fast as possible. I'm glad you came
around, and I'll catch on the flip-flop.
Heimler out.